Chinese manuscript collection 1913-1968
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Chinese Documents from Tucson, Arizona, collection 1913-1968
AZ 376
This collection contains personal papers, business records, and related materials from a Chinese community, the Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association of Tucson, Arizona.
Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association
10 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
A Chinese community of merchants began to develop in Tucson, Ariz. in the later half of the 1800's. To maintain their ethnic identity, Chinese men met in tongs where they could follow their native traditions and speak of home. A similar organization, The Ying On Association was established in the 1930's to serve as a boarding house for single Chinese men upon arrival to Tucson, Ariz. It also served as fraternal organization for elderly Chinese men, and as a source of assistance for members with business problems. A more detailed history of this collection is included with the inventory at the repository.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Personal Papers of Individuals, 1913-1968
Series II: Records of the Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association, 1941-1967
Series III: Records of the Chee Kung Tong and Other Organizations, 1914-1953
Series IV: Game and Gambling Account Books, 1924-1937
Series V: Miscellaneous, Unidentified and Oversize Materials, 1923-1968
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains personal papers, business records, and related materials from a Chinese community, the Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association of Tucson, Arizona. Included are correspondence with family members, legal papers, ledger books, bills, receipts, newsletters, gambling records, photographs of the men, advertising posters, and calendars. Among the individuals documented are Lee Wee Kuan, Lee Wah Ying, Moon Gar Gin, Gin You Chung, and Gin Boon Loon. Organizations represented include the Chee Kung Tong, other tongs, the Suey Ying labor association, the Chinese Anti- Communist League, and many of the Chinese-operated stores and restaurants in Tucson. Gambling records are for cards, checkers, dominos, and chess.
Most materials are in Chinese; some printed forms are in English
Kuan, Lee Wee; Ying, Lee Wah; Gin, Moon Gar; Chung, Gin You; Loon, Gin Boon; Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association -- Records and correspondence; Chee Kung Tong -- Records and correspondence; Tucson Urban Renewal Project; Arizona State Museum; Chinese -- Arizona -- Tucson -- History; Chinese Americans -- Societies, etc.; Chinese American business people -- Arizona -- Tucson; Chinese American families -- Arizona -- Tucson; Chinese Americans -- Photographs; Chinese Americans -- Gambling; Merchants -- Arizona -- Tucson -- History; Gambling -- Arizona -- Tucson -- History; Tucson (Ariz.) -- Emigration and immigration; Tucson (Ariz.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Correspondence; Photographs; Calendars; Accounts
Container List
- Series I: Personal Papers of Individuals, 1913-1968
  - Chiu But Hao (George Chin). 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chou Hing (Edward Joe): Personal papers. 1941-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chou Hing (Edward Joe): Business papers. 1939-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - G. Y. Foo. 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gee Den. 1914-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gee Jen Hang. 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gin Bock Hay. 1914-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gin Bock Kim: Correspondence with Gin Dong Yee. 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gin Bock Kim: Personal papers. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gin Bock Kim: Yin On Association papers. 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Correspondence with Gin Gay Yin (his father) and Gin Fong. 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Correspondence with Yee Shee (his wife). 1936-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Correspondence with Shew Lim (youngest son). 1924-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Social organizations. 1945-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gin Boon Loon: Personal and business papers. 1926-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gin Gay Yin (Gin Fong). 1913-1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gin Hoy Chun (also known as Ho Pock & Charlie Ho): Personal papers. 1931-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gin Hoy Chun: Business papers. 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gin Mon Foo. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gin Poy. 1942 and undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gin Wing. 1953 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gin You Chung: Personal papers. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gin You Chung: Family correspondence. 1914-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gin You Chung: Correspondence with Gin Chong Wum. 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gin You Chung: Miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gin You Chung: Business papers. 1921-1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gin You Chung: Chinese-American Citizens Alliance. 1916-1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gin You Chung: Contributions to charity. 1918-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kim Hong Lim. 1919, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - A. Y. Lee. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Lee Ehr. 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lee Fook Sing (Jim Lee). 1931-1943 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lee Wah (George Lee). 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Tee Shee (his mother). 1936-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Sheung-Tao (his daughter). 1949-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Chew Chong-Ch'ao (his daughter-in-law). 1936-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Chee Suey (his nephew). 1950-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Lee family relatives. 1934-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Lee family relatives. 1950-1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Howard Chow. 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Lee Lam Kwon. 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Correspondence with Ting Hing. 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Business correspondence. 1925-1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Photographs. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    See also Box 19, Oversize.
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Southern Arizona Bank & Trust Co. papers. 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Various banking papers. 1921-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Investments. 1951-1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: City license tax receipts, Tucson, Ariz. 1934-1945 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Miscellaneous bills. 1948-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Receipts for registered mail. 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Personal papers. 1917-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Social organizations. 1919-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Income taxes. 1942-1948 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Legal papers, mortgages, leases, insurance policies. 1922-1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: State, county and city taxes. 1921-1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Pay'n Save Market monthly ledger. 1942-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Pay'n Save check book. 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lee Wee Kuan: Menus and recipe books. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    See also Box 19, Oversize for advertising posters for the Pay'n Save Market.
  - Lee Wah Ying: Personal papers. 1920-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lee Wah Ying: Family correspondence. 1965 and undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lee Wah Ying: Social organizations. 1923-1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lee Wah Ying: Domino Games tickets, receipt books and accounts. 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lee Wah Ying: Miscellaneous account books, keno cards and tickets. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    See also Box 19, Oversize for "Miss Chinatown" posters.
  - Moon Gar Gin (Chester Gin, alias Lee Q. Hing and Chester Lee): Personal papers. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Correspondence with Yee Li Quon (his wife) and Yan Wing Wung (his son). 1953-1967 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Correspondence. 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Naturalization papers. 1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Income taxes. 1951-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Automobile papers. 1953-1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Gin's Cafe. 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Moon Gar Gin: Business and banking papers. 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Quong Ong. 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - William Shew: Correspondence. 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tow Gain Chung. 1921-1925 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Wong Wing Chin. 1917-1954 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Y. B. Yick: Correspondence with Lui Kam Shing and family. 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Yin we Too (Doo Gin). 1925-1954 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Series II: Records of the Ying On Merchants and Labor Benevolent Association, 1941-1967
  - Election papers. 1956, 1965 and undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Applications for membership. 1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Applications for membership. No dates (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Account Book: Money collected. 1949-1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Account Book: Money paid out. 1949 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Banking papers. 1947-1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Financial records. 1941-1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bills and receipts. 1950-1959, 1964, 1966 and undated (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous material. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Financial reports. January 1952-June 1961 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
  - Financial reports. July 1961-December 1964 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Balance sheets, etc. 1950-1953 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Balance sheets, etc. 1956-1959 (Box 9, Folder 6-9)
  - Balance sheets, etc. 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
  - Receipt books for rent. 1950-1956, 1960, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Receipt books for yearly dues. 1951-1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Duplicate rent receipts. August 1959-March 1960 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Receipt book with names of those paying yearly dues to the national Ying On Association. August-December 1947 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Receipt books for the sale and purchase of sesame oil. 1947, 1950, 1955-1958, 1960 (Box 11)
    See also Box 19 Oversize for charts listing membership names and addresses and officers. Box 20 Oversize lists the names, addresses, and telephone numbers of the members of the Ying On Tucson group.
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Individually signed notes for "drinks on account." (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: A-1 Distributors, Inc. 1956 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Buxton-Smith Merchandise Co. 1953-1956 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Pueblo Sales, Inc., Wholesale Liquor. 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Ritter-Walker Distributing Co., Wholesale Liquor. 1953-1956 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: United Liquor Supply, Inc. 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Various food and drink. 1951-1956 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz, Bills and receipts: Maintenance, etc. 1951-1967 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz: Daily balance sheets. July 1953 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Ying On Club, Tucson, Ariz: Ledger of accounts with various companies. 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Series III: Records of the Chee Kung Tong and Other Organizations, 1914-1953
  - Chee Kung Tong: Miscellaneous. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chee Kung Tong: Edict to the branch in Tucson. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Chee Kung Tong: Bills and receipts. 1924-1933 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Chee Kung Tong: Blank receipt books. ca. 1920 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Chee Kung Tong: Revised By-Laws and list of members. 1920 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Chee Kung Tong: Ledger. 1914-1924 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Chee Kung Tong: General account book. 1920-1934 (Box 14)
    See also Box 19 Oversize for photographs of the 1923 conference.
  - Chinese Anti-Communist League, Tucson Branch: Newsletter. 1952 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Suey Ying (Labor) Association: Book with accounts, signatures of members attending meetings and an explanation of the organization's composition in relation to the Sing Lee Company. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Suey Ying (Labor) Association: Miscellaneous items. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Hop Sing Tong: Miscellaneous items. 1934, 1951-1953 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Hoy Sun Ning Yung Association, Los Angeles: By-Laws. 1928 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Hoy Sun Ning Yung Association, Los Angeles: Photographs. 1930 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Gin Sun Hall Tong: Newsletter. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Kuo Ming Tong: New Year's Festival items. 1951 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    See also Box 19 Oversize for photograph of 1927 conference.
  - Hop Chong Tong: Ledger. 1915 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Game and Gambling Account Books, 1924-1937
  - Chinese Checker Game Account Book. September 25, 1936 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Various game cards. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Chinese Chess Game Account Book. June 1, 1935 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Chinese Chess Game Account Book. September 27, 1935 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Chinese Domino Game Receipt Book. April-July 1934 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Chinese Domino Game Receipt Book, proceeds to go to the "making of a bronze idol." (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Yeh Yeh Co. Chinese Chess Game Account Book. June 1, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Yeh Yeh Co. Account Book. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified gambling accounts (2 books). 1924-1926 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Series V: Miscellaneous, Unidentified and Oversize Material, 1923-1968
  - Miscellaneous Material, 1937-1957
    - Chung-Hsing Co. General Account Ledger. 1937 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Pekin Cafe, Tucson, bills and receipts. 1951-1957 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Tom Wing's Market, Tucson, bills and receipts. 1943 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    - P'ingan Restaurant daily worksheet. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Prescription labels for herbs and newspaper articles giving medical advice. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings dealing with issues in China and the local Chinese community. 1950's (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Material, 1924-1961
    - Photographs. (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
    - Balance sheet and currency transfer form. 1961 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Two Account Books. January-June 1949 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Personal Accounts Ledger. 1949 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Account Book. 1924 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Menu book for an unidentified restaurant. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Three blank receipt books. (Box 18)
  - Oversize Material, 1923-1968
    - Ying On Merchants & Labor Benevolent Association of Tucson membership lists. 1952-1955 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Loan Bonds of the Republic of China. 1938 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Liberty Bonds of the Republic of China. 1937 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Advertising posters for Pay'n Save Grocery and Meat Market. 1930's-1940's (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Calendars and advertising posters for various markets, liquor stores and cafes in Tucson. 1930-1960 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Calendars from Soleng Realty and Trust Co. in Tucson. 1955, 1960, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Calendars from San Francisco. 1950, 1954 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Calendars from Southern Arizona Bank & Trust Co. 1959-1960, 1962-1968 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Calendars from Valley National Bank. 1954-1955, 1958-1959, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Calendar from Lee's Market, Eloy, Arizona. 1964 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Calendar from Howard Hom Insurance Agency, Tucson. 1966 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Posters for "Miss Chinatown" San Francisco. 1955-1968 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous photographs. (Box 19, Folder 12)
      Includes photo of:
      Chee Kung Tong Conference, 1923
      Kuo Ming Tong Conference, 1927
      Lee Wee Kuan
      Wong Fong
      Unidentified young Chinese men
    - Gin Family: Native settlement maps and corresponding dialogue, used for interrogation for immigration. No date (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Calendar and posters printed in China. (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Chart listing names, addresses, and telephone numbers of local members of the Tucson Ying On Association. (Box 20)